

# Marcos Chiñas Hernández

+52 971 145 42 13

marcosch@lcg.unam.mx <u>chmarcos.github.io</u>

Av. Universidad 898, Chamilpa, Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico.

# **Profile**

I'm a specialist in Genomic Sciences, I have guided myself to acquire skills in experimental work and bioinformatics on interesting topics, learning from admirable people.

I'm motivated to participate in new challenging projects, to achieve the goals I work hard and independently.

### **RESEARCH INTEREST**

- Cancer
- Immunology
- Gene regulation
- Transcriptomics, sc-genomics
- Software development
- Genome editing
- Deep Learning

# Research experience

### **FEB 2020 - PRESENT**

Advisor: Fidel Alejandro Sánchez | Sequencing and Bioinformatics Unit, Institute of Biotechnology UNAM, Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico.

I worked in the regulatory profile of prostate cancer cell line under AZD5363 treatment. I worked with RNA seq data and I carried out the enrichment analysis, interaction network using Cytoscape, and transcription factor activity analysis. I used R and R Markdown to create an automated report that is reproducible and applicable in other projects. I'm comparing the transcriptomic profile against 6 pancreatic cancer cell lines under AZD5363 treatment to contrast responses and identify resistance mechanisms.

### **DEC 2019 - IAN 2020**

Advisor: Antônio Mauro Rezende | Instituto Aggeu Magalhães FIOCRUZ, Recife, Pernanbuco, Brazil.

I worked with Illumina data, performed data quality with FastQC, aligned reads with STAR, and used edgeR and DESeq2 for differential expression analysis.

### SEP 2019 - DEC 2019

Advisor: Sabino Pacheco Guillén | Department of Molecular Microbiology, Institute of Biotechnology UNAM, Cuernavaca, Morelos. Mexico.

In this project, I worked on the design of guide RNA and in vitro tests for CRISPR-Cas9.

### **MAR 2018 - JUN 2018**

Advisor: Sabino Pacheco Guillén | Department of Molecular Microbiology, Institute of Biotechnology UNAM, Cuernavaca, Morelos. Mexico.

Learning of molecular biology techniques (PCR, Gel electrophoresis, DNA extraction, Cloning of Cry genes, and Protein purification).

# Education

#### **UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAM ON GENOMIC SCIENCES**

2017 - Today

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM). Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico. Studying the eighth semester.

### Impact of LCG graduates on research

International assessment of the LCG

Global Average: 9.33/10

## HIGH SCHOOL AT "BACHILLERATO GENERAL ISTMEÑA"

2014 - 2017

Tehuantepec, Oaxaca, Mexico.

Grade: 10/10 Best high school average

# Programming skills

### **ADVANCED LEVEL**

- R
- Python
- Linux commands

#### **BASIC LEVEL**

- Perl
- C
- PHP
- SQL

# Bioinformatics skills

- Statistics in R
- Differential expression analysis (edgeR, DESeq2)
- Genome assembly and annotation
- Data visualization: ggplot2, shiny
- · Git & Github
- Static web pages using Jekyll & Github
- Variant analysis
- Bacterial typing

### **Basic knowledge:**

- Single-cell analysis
- Phylogenetics
- Structural bioinformatics
- Motif discovery and ChIPseq analysis

# Languages

- Spanish (Native)
- English ( Speak: Intermediate, Writing: Intermediate, Reading: Advanced)
- Portuguese (Basic level)

# **Awards**

 UNAM-DGECI Initiation to Research, Summer-Autumn 2021. <u>Results</u> ID:418073593

# **Undergraduate courses**

Cell Biology I and II, Biochemistry, Molecular Biology I and II, Introduction to genomic, Genetics, Principles of Evolution, Phylogenetic, Human Genomics, Epigenetics, Systems biology, Programming Principles, Computing, R, Principles of Statistics and Probability, Statistics, Introduction to bioinformatics, Bioinformatics I and II, Calculus, Linear algebra, Differential Equations I and II, Applications of genomics I and II (national genomics seminars), Frontiers in genomics I and II (international genomics seminars), Immunology, Genome assembly, Functional genomics.

# **Additional courses**

- Coursera, Using Shiny to Plot Differential Gene Expression
- Johns Hopkins University (JHU) Command Line Tools for Genomic Data Science
- JHU Genomic Data Science with Galaxy
- JHU Understanding Prostate Cancer
- JHU Algorithms for DNA Sequencing
- JHU Python for Genomic Data Science
- JHU Bioconductor for Genomic Data Science
- JHU Statistics for Genomic Data Science
- JHU Introduction to Genomic Technologies
- <u>DTU, Whole-genome sequencing of bacterial genomes tools and application</u>
- Harvard, Data Science: Productivity Tools
- Harvard, Data Science: Visualization

# References

# FIDEL ALEJANDRO SÁNCHEZ FLORES

Massive Sequencing and Bioinformatics Unit Institute of Biotechnology - UNAM Cuernavaca, Morelos, México alejandro.sanchez@ibt.unam.mx, +52 (55) 5622 7864, +52 (777) 3291864

### **ANTÔNIO MAURO REZENDE**

Microbiology Department Institute Aggeu Magalhães - FIOCRUZ Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil antonio.rezende@fiocruz.br, +55 81 2101 2698

### SABINO PACHECO GUILLÉN

Molecular Microbiology Department Institute of Biotechnology - UNAM Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico sabino.pacheco@ibt.unam.mx, +52 (55) 5622 7600, +52 (777) 329 1600

# VNIVERADAD NACIONAL AVENOMA DE MEXICO

# Licenciatura en Ciencias Genómicas

February, 2021

Subject: Academic Records

### To whom it may concern:

This is to certify that **Mr. Marcos Chiñas Hernández**, with file number **418073593** is currently studying the eighth semester of the Undergraduate Program on Genomic Sciences of the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM). This program comprises eight semesters with a total number of 384 credits.

Next, the grades obtained (on a 1 to 10 scale) on the First to seventh Semesters by Mr. Chiñas are listed as requested:

First Semester:	Credits	Grades
Cellular Biology	08	09
Biochemistry	08	09
Molecular Biology	08	09
Mathematics 1	08	10
Programming Principles	08	07
Seminar 1	08	09
Second Semester:		
Computation	08	07
Genetics	08	08
Mathematics 2	08	10
Statistics Principles	08	10
Evolution Principles	08	09
Seminar 2	08	10
Third Semester:		
Bioinformatics and Statistics 1	08	09
Evolutionary Genomics 1	08	08
Functional Genomics 1	08	09
Mathematics 3	08	08
Genomics Models	08	09
Seminar 3	08	10
Fourth Semester:		
Bioinformatics and Statistics 2	08	09
Evolutionary Genomics 2	08	08
Functional Genomics 2	08	08
Human Genomics	08	09
Mathematics 4	08	10
Seminar 4	08	10

Centro de Ciencias Genómicas, Ave. Universidad 2001, Col. Chamilpa. 62210 Cuernavaca, Mor. México. <a href="http://www.lcg.unam.mx">http://www.lcg.unam.mx</a> Correo electrónico: coordinador@lcg.unam.mx Tel./Fax: (777) 329 08 27



# Licenciatura en Ciencias Genómicas

Fifth semester:	Credits	Grades
Genomics Applications 1	08	10
Genomics Applications 2	08	10
Frontiers in Genomics 1	08	09
Frontiers in Genomics 2	08	09
Integrative Genomics 1	08	10
Integrative Genomics 2	08	10
Sixth semester:		
Genomics Applications 3	08	10
Genomics Applications 4	08	10
Frontiers in Genomics 3	08	10
Frontiers in Genomics 4	08	10
Integrative Genomics 3	08	10
Integrative Genomics 4	08	10
Seventh Semester:		
Research Project 1	06	10
Research project 2	06	10
Research Project 3	06	10
Selected Topics 1	10	10
Selected Topics 2	10	10
Research Seminars 1	10	10

Global Average: 9.33 Credits: 87.50%

If any further information is needed, please contact me.

Dr. Pablo Vinuesa Fleischmann

Coordinator of the Undergraduate Program

on Genomic Sciences

Centro De Ciencias Genómicas, UNAM